<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Brief history of Presbytery and Independency from their first original to this time shewing I. wherein and the reasons why they separate from the Church of England, II. wherein they differ from each other : with some remarks on the late heads of agreement assented to by the united ministers of both perswasions ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 85 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29456</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4598</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7644</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11980799</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11980799</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51818</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29456)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51818)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 56:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Brief history of Presbytery and Independency from their first original to this time shewing I. wherein and the reasons why they separate from the Church of England, II. wherein they differ from each other : with some remarks on the late heads of agreement assented to by the united ministers of both perswasions ...</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Edward Faulkner,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Presbyterianism --  History.</term>
               <term>Congregationalism --  History.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England --  History.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51818:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BRIEF HISTORY OF PRESBYTERY AND INDEPENDENCY, From their firſt Original, to this Time. SHEWING,
<list>
                  <item>I. Wherein, and the Reaſons why they Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. Wherein they differ from each other.</item>
               </list> WITH Some Remarks on the late Heads of Agreement, Aſſented to by the United Miniſters of both PERSWASIONS.</p>
            <p>Written at the Requeſt, and for the Satisfaction of a Private Friend, and now made publick for General Information.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Edward Faulkner,</hi> 1691.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:51818:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:51818:2"/>
            <head>A BRIEF HISTORY OF PRESBYTERY AND INDEPENDENCY, &amp;c.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>TO give a full Hiſtory of <hi>Nonconformity</hi> to the <hi>Church of England,</hi> ſince the firſt Reformation, is both impracticable and impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, in ſo ſmall a Treatiſe; take here only an <hi>Eſſay</hi> to it, in a Compendious Epitome: Begin we with that Reformation tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported from that of <hi>Luther</hi>'s in <hi>Germany,</hi> unto our King <hi>Edward</hi> the VI. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <div n="1" type="remark">
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:51818:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>Remark 1.</head>
                  <p>He is truly ſtyled a <hi>ſecond Joſiah,</hi> whom <hi>Cardan,</hi> though a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> yet had ſo much of a <hi>Philoſopher</hi> in him, as to Admire for a <hi>None-ſuch</hi> in Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhments, ſaying, in a Tranſport, of him [<hi>Not only</hi> England, <hi>but the</hi> World <hi>has reaſon to lament the loſs of ſuch an hopeful Bloſſom, ſo early Blaſted.</hi> [Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as a Prelatical Doctor of our Country, and a pretended <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> ſeem'd to rejoyce at it, rather than bewail it as an <hi>Infelicity,</hi> [That <hi>he was ſo ſoon Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded by Q.</hi> Mary, <hi>a Bloody</hi> Popiſh <hi>Queen,</hi>] Characterizing him as one <hi>ill principl'd</hi> in himſelf, and eaſily inclin'd to embrace ſuch Counſels, as would have proved <hi>pernicious</hi> to the Church, ſo ſlanders him with <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Heyline Hiſt. of Ref. Preface &amp; pag.</hi> 131. &amp;c. no Reaſon can be rendred why <hi>Cardan</hi> ſhould out ſhine <hi>Heylin,</hi> in Admiring this <hi>Young King,</hi> but becauſe ſuch a Spirit of Reformation began to bud in him, as if it had bloſſom'd, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Fruit, would in all probability have Reformed the Church throughly, according to her primitive Pattern, and ſo dear was the <hi>Diana</hi> of the Churches Splendour and worldly Pomp in that Day, that a <hi>Popiſh</hi> Queen who would Eſtabliſh it, was more welcome than ſuch an hopeful King, whom they fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, would Reduce it to the <hi>firſt Inſtitution: Non erat ſic ab Initio. It was not ſo from the Beginning,</hi> though ſuch profound Piety ſhone forth in this Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Prince in ſo convincing a luſtre, as <hi>Mother-Church</hi> her ſelf could not bribe that <hi>Popiſh</hi> Foreign Philoſopher, but he was conſtrained to afford this Royal Enemy his due Encomium: Yet his Regal Dignity, or Innocent Piety can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſecure him from Severe Cenſures, out of the Mouths of <hi>Engliſh Divines,</hi> under a Tincture of <hi>Prelacy:</hi> Nor was this all, but that King's Godly Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle the Duke of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> did ſuffer hard things, and at laſt Death it ſelf, by ſuch as were ſowred by the like Leaven: In both which caſes, the venom of a Perſecuting Spirit, had a prepoſterous Operation, <hi>working upwvrd,</hi> both againſt a <hi>Pious Prince,</hi> and againſt a <hi>Pious Protector:</hi> They both were Spew'd upon by Men of this Brann, whereas when there is a poſſeſſion of Power in their hands, then this poyſonous Principle is for <hi>working Downward,</hi> caſting forth Cart Loads of Excrements upon ſuch as under their power, as the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quel will ſufficiently demonſtrate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="remark">
                  <head>Remark 2.</head>
                  <p>'Tis well obſerved, that the ſhortneſs of K. <hi>Edward</hi>'s Life, prevented him of an opportunity for a thorough Reformation. [<hi>Notwithſtanding the high Places were not yet Remov'd,</hi>] as 'tis oft ſaid in the <hi>Books</hi> of <hi>Kings,</hi> and <hi>Chronicles</hi>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:51818:3"/> of the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah:</hi> Mr. <hi>Martin Luther</hi> hath this Paſſage in his Hiſtory, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 283. That <hi>Edward</hi> VI. was a Storm that tore up <hi>Popiſh</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy by the Roots, yet a top Root remain'd entire with the Stock which bare of the old Soil of <hi>Papacy,</hi> yet tranſplanted into the new Mold of Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, began to flouriſh again, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and may it not be ſaid, that he had not time nor opportunity to do little more than to lop off the Branches of <hi>Popery,</hi> becauſe he dyed when but <hi>Sixteen Years</hi> old, ſo leaving the Root, it preſently ſprung up again when his Siſter <hi>Mary</hi> Succeeded him in the Throne.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="remark">
                  <head>Remark 3.</head>
                  <p>Dr. <hi>Thomas Fuller,</hi> an <hi>Epiſcopal Divine,</hi> in his Hiſtory of this <hi>Edward</hi> the VI. hath this Paſſage, [For this Young King to Reform all at once, had been the ready way to Reform nothing at all; but now (ſaith he) there is more Light, more number of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> leſs fear of <hi>Papists,</hi> therefore a thorough Reformation may now be more probable and practicable; inſtead whereof, ſhall we ſtill run back to <hi>Rome: Hinc illae lachrimae,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="remark">
                  <head>Remark 4.</head>
                  <p>'Tis true, King <hi>Henry</hi> the VIII. broke the Ice for his young Son, by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning the <hi>Lord's Prayer,</hi> the <hi>Creed,</hi> and the <hi>Ten Commandments,</hi> to be tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated into the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue, and to be taught unto the Pariſhioners by all the <hi>Parſons and Vicars:</hi> Even this ſmall ſtep coſt a Rebellion at <hi>Lincoln, York, Hull,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Tanta molis erat Romanam condere gentem:</hi> The Work of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is a Work of great difficulty.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="remark">
                  <head>Remark 5.</head>
                  <p>Paſs we over Queen <hi>Marys</hi> Reign, which was a Reign of Deformation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and come to the Reign of our <hi>Engliſh Deborah,</hi> Famous Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> who renew'd and reviv'd K. <hi>Edward</hi>'s Reformation again, but ſo retarded ſhe was by ſo many Remora's in her Reforming Work, that ſhe could not ſtep up to the <hi>Pattern in the Mount,</hi> the Sacred Scriptures, the Word of God, which is [<hi>Regula Regulans &amp; Regulata,</hi>] the Rule Ruling, as well as the Rule Ruled: 'Tis <hi>Index ſui &amp; obliqui,</hi> giving the trueſt Indication both of its own ſtraightneſs, and of others crookedneſs: But alas, <hi>Prudentials,</hi> and <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks</hi> of <hi>State,</hi> then prevailed againſt that weaker Royal Sex, the over-top<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Vogue was then, [<hi>New Wine muſt be gently poured into old Bottles,</hi>] leaſt the ſtrength of the Liquor, being advantag'd by the violence of the Infuſion,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51818:4"/> break the Veſſel, <hi>&amp;c. Reformation</hi> (cryed the <hi>Grandees</hi> of that Day) muſt be made by degrees, and <hi>State-Politicians</hi> muſt deal with the <hi>Body-Politick,</hi> (when ſick, and ſwollen with Diſtempers) as the Skilful <hi>Chyrurgeon</hi> dealeth with an <hi>Hydropick Perſon,</hi> whoſe Body is almoſt drown'd with a Deluge of Water; the Cure is <hi>done by degrees,</hi> ſome <hi>Tap</hi> or <hi>Sluce</hi> muſt be opened, yet not to let go all at once, leaſt the violent Effluvium, or flowing forth of the natural Spirits (together with the Peccant Morbiſick Humour, conſtantly conſequent) ſhould deſtroy the Patient, and endanger him upon dry ground more than in thoſe almoſt drowning Waters; but the Method is a <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the opening of a ſmall Tap or Hole in the Skin, which may ſo run as to drain the Body gradually of its Dropſie, and by inſenſible degrees drawing out not above a Pint at a time, and never more at once, though many Gollons be deſigned for Evacuation: So <hi>Politicians</hi> will not make over large leaps at once.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="remark">
                  <head>Remark 6.</head>
                  <p>'Tis an excellent Obſervation of Famous Mr. <hi>Fuller</hi> concerning theſe <hi>firſt Reformers,</hi> whom he compareth to the Patriarch <hi>Jacob,</hi> who would not over drive his Tender Flock, ſaying, [<hi>I dare not march my Lord</hi> Eſau<hi>'s pace.</hi>] It may be eaſily preſumed, that <hi>Jacob</hi> lookt upon his Brother as one very nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of foot, becauſe he ſo delighted to lead an Huntſman's Life, and lived ſo much in Hunting his ſwift Game: Though <hi>Jacob</hi> himſelf could have <hi>lift up his feet</hi> (as he did when refreſhed with the <hi>Viſion</hi> of the Ladder, <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.12. and 29.1 <hi>Hebr.</hi>) and walk'd <hi>Eſau</hi>'s pace, yet would he not force his fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Flocks to keep pace with <hi>Eſau:</hi> Even ſo (ſaith Mr. <hi>Fuller</hi>) thoſe <hi>firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers</hi> found <hi>England</hi> ſetled upon the <hi>Lees,</hi> having been long nouzell'd up in <hi>Superſtition,</hi> &amp;c. ſo could not be look'd upon as capable of a ſudden and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Alteration, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Fuller<hi>'s Church Hiſt. Cent.</hi> 16. <hi>B.</hi> 7. <hi>pag.</hi> 374. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all this, theſe Reformers have Right to a due Veneration for that moſt excellent Reformation they made in the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the Church, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering what <hi>Anakins,</hi> and what <hi>Goliahs</hi> they had at that time to contend with, and how the whole World almoſt in that Day did <hi>wonder after the Beaſt,</hi> Revel. 13.3. Yea, and a long and continued Cuſtom for many Ages (ſaving the ſhort Parentheſis of K. <hi>Edward</hi>'s Reign) of training up every Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration in Idolatry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> had made it a <hi>Law</hi> or <hi>Preſcription,</hi> yet were theſe <hi>Reformers</hi> moſt <hi>eminent</hi> Inſtruments in God's Hand, to carry on ſo couragiouſly a <hi>Doctrinal Reformation,</hi> wherein they threw down the Walls of <hi>Jericho,</hi> by the ſounding of <hi>Rams Horns,</hi> and <hi>put to flight the Armys of the Aliens,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="remark">
                  <head>Remark 7.</head>
                  <p>It muſt evermore be acknowledged to the Eternal Honour of thoſe choice and chief Champions of the true Church in that Day. How they knock'd
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51818:4"/> down the <hi>prime Pillars,</hi> or rather <hi>Catter pillars</hi> of the <hi>Romiſh Church,</hi> with their <hi>look beyond Luther,</hi> &amp;c. who, when the <hi>Romanits</hi> ask'd them, <hi>Where, was your Religion before</hi> Luther? Anſwered, it was in the Sacred Scriptures, where their <hi>Romiſh Religion</hi> could not be found, which they demonſtrated to them by undeniable Arguments, inſomuch, that when the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> were ſenſibly foiled, and beaten out of the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> they cry'd for their only <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve,</hi> ſaying. [Let us forſake <hi>that Field</hi> wherein we are defeated with <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt.</hi> it is <hi>written in Gods Word,</hi> &amp;c. and let us rally all our Forces in the Field of the <hi>Ancient Fathers,</hi> wherein we <hi>may master them.</hi>] Here again the Battel was renew'd, and here again the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> were beaten out of their ſtrong hold of Tradition, for the firſt Six Hundred Years after <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which is the whole term of time that deſerves the Title of Antiquity: In this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie our Learned <hi>Whittaker</hi> acted ſo eminently, that his <hi>Antagoniſt Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> had his Picture in his Study, with this Inſcription upon it, [<hi>Quanquam Haereticum, Doctum tamen habeo Adverſarium:</hi>] Though this <hi>Whittaker</hi> be an <hi>Heretick,</hi> yet I find him a Learned one.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="remark">
                  <head>Remark 8.</head>
                  <p>Beſides him many more Famous Worthys ſhone forth in their Orb in that day, as the <hi>Queens Jewel,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Juel</hi> and others, who all did excellently as to the <hi>Doctrinal Reformation,</hi> from the Corruptions of the <hi>Romiſh Church;</hi> but as to the <hi>Diſcipline</hi> of a Goſpel-Church, they did not ſo much meddle with, perhaps, looking upon it as not pertaining to the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> or <hi>Being,</hi> but only to the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, or <hi>well being</hi> of the Church; and hence it came to paſs, that ſo much <hi>Romiſh Rubbiſh</hi> ſtill remain'd unremov'd, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whereby a Foundation was laid among the tendereſt part both of <hi>Paſtors</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> for <hi>Nonconformity</hi> from thoſe Altitudinarian <hi>Conformiſts,</hi> who had writ upon their <hi>Pillars,</hi> a [<hi>Ne plus Ultra,</hi>] being reſolv'd not to ſtir one ſtep farther into the Work of <hi>Reformation:</hi> Whereas this ſeem'd a Sullenneſs much differing from the practice of their Piouſly Learned Predeceſſors; as (<hi>1ſt.</hi>) Holy Father <hi>Latimer</hi> had not reſted in the Reformation made by K. <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. only Engliſhing the <hi>Lords Prayer, Creed,</hi> and <hi>Ten Commandments</hi> to the People, but he perſwaded K. <hi>Edward</hi> VI. to ſtep farther, that the People might have the whole <hi>Divine Service</hi> in their <hi>Mother Tongue,</hi> &amp;c. Nor were <hi>bleſſed Bucer,</hi> and <hi>holy Hooker</hi> ſo fully ſatisfy'd with the firſt Purgation of the <hi>Liturgy,</hi> after it was extracted out of the <hi>Popiſh Maſs-Book</hi> by K. <hi>Edward</hi>'s <hi>Divines,</hi> they could not reſt contented ſo, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded the King to a ſecond Purgation, as the <hi>ſecond Edition</hi> of the <hi>Service-Book</hi> ſheweth: Nor was Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> willing to reſt in that <hi>ſecond Edition,</hi> of K. <hi>Edward</hi>'s, but Reformed divers things in it, though her Royal Brother had given it a ſecond refining: Nor did this <hi>Queens Divines</hi> (<hi>Juel, Bentham, Pilkinton,</hi> &amp;c.) bring in their <hi>Edition</hi> with any ſuch high Commendatory
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51818:5"/> Character, as [<hi>Omnia bene,</hi>] All are ſo well, as needs no Amendment, when they brought it to her Majeſty for Authorizing it by her Royal Authority, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="remark">
                  <head>Remark 9.</head>
                  <p>Beſides all this, I might mention many more Amendments, which Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Mr. <hi>Hugh</hi>'s computeth, were it not that it would too much ſwell this ſmall Diſcourſe, I refer only to it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> from whence we may <hi>mark,</hi> That as there was a [<hi>plus ultra,</hi>] or a ſteping farther all along, in Reforming the means of Gods Worſhip, taken for granted; ſo there was a kind of <hi>Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity</hi> found firſt in thoſe Royal Perſons, namely K. <hi>Edward,</hi> not conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that Reformation made by his Royal Father K. <hi>Henry</hi> the VIII, and Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s not conforming to that of her Royal Brother K. <hi>Edward</hi> the VI: Nor ought we to <hi>Deſpiſe that Day of ſmall things,</hi> Zach. 4.10. but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Adore Divine Goodneſs that reveal'd ſo much to them in their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſtep out of <hi>Popery.</hi> As we ſay of <hi>Luther,</hi> God is more to be Admired <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealing ſo much of the Myſtery of Divine Truth, to him more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> that main Fundamental point of <hi>Juſtification,</hi> &amp;c. (wherein he is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lent in his Comment upon the Epiſtle to the <hi>Galathians</hi>) than for leaving him to his own Miſtakes about <hi>Conſubſtantiation:</hi> But the <hi>firſt</hi> grand <hi>Nonconformiſt</hi> to the Eſtabliſhed Church of <hi>England,</hi> under that <hi>Proteſtant Queen,</hi> was Mr. <hi>Tho. Cartwright,</hi> who had her Royal Approbation at a Commencement in <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> and after became <hi>Profeſſor of Divinity</hi> there, and in his Lectures, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing occaſion'd to diſcover his <hi>Nonconformity</hi> about <hi>Church Diſcipline,</hi> the Heads of the Univerſity took it heinouſly, as dangerous to the <hi>Hierarchy,</hi> and for which, notwithſtanding his Univerſally admired Merit and Veneration, they got him at laſt Expell'd the Univerſity, when Dr. <hi>Whitgift</hi> was <hi>Vice Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor.</hi> Now when his Miniſtry was thus obſtructed in <hi>England,</hi> he travell'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Sea, where he Conforted with Famous <hi>Beza,</hi> who gave him this Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, [<hi>The Sun never ſhone upon a more Learned Man,</hi>] in a Letter <hi>Beza</hi> wrote to his Friend in <hi>England, Secondly,</hi> Many more <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> appear after upon the Stage, as Mr. <hi>Deering,</hi> Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> the <hi>Martyrologiſt,</hi> with others, who drew up an Admonition to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> for the Reformation of the <hi>Church,</hi> which Dr. <hi>Whitgift</hi> (then made Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi>) Anſwered, to which a Reply was made.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:51818:5"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>THIS Chapter is a more particular Hiſtory of the firſt Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration from the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> as it was then conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted, in the Reign of Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> by the Non-conformiſts of that time, who were partly of the <hi>Presbyterial,</hi> and partly of the <hi>Congregational</hi> Judgment, which the ſequel may demonſtrate.</p>
               <div n="1" type="remark">
                  <p>The firſt <hi>Remark</hi> is, the Non-conformity of Mr. <hi>Cartwright,</hi> in theſe following <hi>Propoſitions,</hi> under his own hand-writing were,</p>
                  <p n="1">As (1.) That the Names of <hi>Arch-biſhops</hi> and of <hi>Arch-deacons</hi> ought to be aboliſhed with all their Offices and Exerciſes of Power.</p>
                  <p n="2">(2.) That the Names of the Legitimate Miniſters in the Church, ſuch as are <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Deacons,</hi> ſo far as they are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from thoſe Functions that are ſimply ſet down in the Word of God, ought to be removed, and reduced to their firſt Apoſtolical Inſtitution; namely, That the <hi>Deacons</hi> ſhould <hi>ſerve</hi> the Tables of the Poor, and the <hi>Biſhops</hi> give themſelves to the <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Prayer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">(3.) That the Government of the Church ought not to be committed to the <hi>Chancellours</hi> of <hi>Biſhops,</hi> or to the <hi>Officers</hi> of <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacons,</hi> but to a fit Miniſtry and Presbytery of the ſame Church.</p>
                  <p n="4">(4.) That no Miniſter ought to be a Wanderer, or running at random, but every one ſhould be fixed to his own proper place.</p>
                  <p n="5">(5.) No Man ought to make himſelf Miniſter of any People by a <hi>Mandamus</hi> from the <hi>Sovereign</hi> to the Electors of ſuch to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">(6.) Miniſters ought not to be made by the Authority and Power of <hi>Biſhops</hi> onely, much leſs in the <hi>Biſhop</hi>'s Study, or any private place; but ſhould be choſen by the <hi>Church</hi> it ſelf, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Concluding thus, That every Man is bound by his Calling to reform thoſe Deformities; to wit, <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> by their Power, <hi>Miniſters</hi> by their Preaching, and <hi>People</hi> by their Prayers. All jointly muſt promote this aforeſaid <hi>Reformation:</hi> Theſe were the Crimes for which Doctor <hi>Whitgift,</hi> then <hi>Vice-chancellour,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled Mr. <hi>Cartwright</hi> out of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> after which, K. <hi>James,</hi> then King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſent for him, profering to make him <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor</hi> of Divinity in the Univerſity of St. <hi>Andrews;</hi> and the <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51818:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> of Dublin</hi> alſo ſent for him into <hi>Ireland,</hi> profering him Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment in that Kingdom: but the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Leiceſter</hi> fixed him (after his Return from Travel beyond Sea) making him Maſter of the <hi>Hoſpital</hi> at <hi>Warwick,</hi> at which time that peſtilent piece the <hi>Rhemiſh Teſtament</hi> came forth, and look'd on of ſuch dangerous conſequence, that it required the ableſt Pen to anſwer it. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Sir <hi>Francis Walſingham</hi> (the Queen's right-hand and eye) courted Mr. <hi>Cartwright</hi> to the Undertaking, ſent him an Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pound (few ſuch gifts now a days to <hi>Non-conformiſts</hi>) to furniſh him for the Work. Yea, the Learned <hi>Doctors</hi> of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge</hi> and the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Suffolk</hi> exhorted him to undertake it Notwithſtanding all this Arch biſhop <hi>Whitgift</hi> ſent him a politive <hi>Prohibition,</hi> fearing, ſaith Dr. <hi>Fuller,</hi> leſt any of his Dry Blows and Diſtaſtfull Paſſages ſhot at <hi>Rome,</hi> might glance at <hi>Canterbury,</hi> Ch. Hiſt. <hi>Cent.</hi> 16. <hi>pag.</hi> 171.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="remark">
                  <p>The ſecond <hi>Remark</hi> is, I, to avoid prolixity, am conſtrained to omit the many Stories of <hi>Non-conformity</hi> form <hi>Henry</hi> the VIII's Reformation, in his aboliſhing the <hi>Pope</hi>'s <hi>Supremacy,</hi> and the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of <hi>Abbies,</hi> &amp;c. And of that under <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, which I have by me from <hi>Stow,</hi> Dr. <hi>Heylin,</hi> Sir <hi>Richard Baker,</hi> &amp;c. but beg leave to inſert one or two Stories out of peeviſh <hi>Peter Heylin,</hi> ſaying, The People might have reſted in the Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, if <hi>Calvin</hi>'s pragmatical Spirit (as he ſtyles it) had not interpoſed: He firſt began to quarrel at ſome Paſſages in the <hi>Liturgy,</hi> and afterwards never left ſoliciting the <hi>Lord Protector</hi> and the <hi>Univerſities,</hi> till he had laid the firſt foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the <hi>Zuinglian</hi> Faction, to which they were encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the <hi>Indulgence</hi> granted to <hi>John Alaſco,</hi> who, bringing with him a mixed multitude of <hi>Poles</hi> and <hi>Germans,</hi> obtained the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilege of a [<hi>Non conformiſt</hi>] <hi>Church,</hi> for him and his people, diſtinct from the <hi>Church of England</hi> in Government and Form of Worſhip: This much animated (ſaith he) the <hi>Zuinglian</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpellers to practiſe firſt upon the Church, and, being countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the Earl of <hi>Warwick,</hi> then quarrelled with Epiſcopal Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits, againſt <hi>Copes, Tippets, Surplices,</hi> &amp;c. but at laſt fell upon the <hi>Altars</hi> which were left ſtanding (as they had been in times of Popery) by the Rules of the <hi>Liturgy:</hi> Then were ſome rude People encouraged (ſaith he) under-hand by the Grandees of the Court to beat down ſome <hi>Altars,</hi> which made way for an Order of the <hi>Council Table</hi> to take down the reſt, and ſet up Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51818:6"/> in their places: Hereupon the coſtly Coverings of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, together with their rich Prieſtly Grarments (made of Cloth of Tiſſue, Cloth of Gold and Silver or embroidered Velvet, the meaneſt of them being made of Silk or Sattin, with ſome decent trimming) were handſomely converted to private uſe, for Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, Cuſhions, Coverlids, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for the Court Lords: This change (ſaith he) drew on the Alteration of the former <hi>Liturgy,</hi> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt as unpleaſing to the <hi>Zuinglian</hi> Faction (ſo he brands the <hi>Puritans</hi> of that day by this Name) as the former was. In which conjuncture of Affairs K. <hi>Ed.</hi> died, whoſe death, ſaith he, I cannot reckon for an Infelicity to the <hi>Church of England,</hi> for he, being ill-principled in himſelf, and eaſily inclined to embrace ſuch Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, would have put down Biſhopricks alſo, and left the Church to her natural Nakedneſs. Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi>'s <hi>Preface</hi> to his <hi>Hiſtory of Reformation.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="remark">
                  <p>The third <hi>Remark</hi> is from Dr. <hi>Helyn,</hi> pag. 72, 75, 79, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> After he had made the <hi>Lord Protector</hi> a moſt ſacrilegious perſon, in pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling down <hi>Churches</hi> wherewith to build his <hi>Somerſet</hi>-Houſe in the <hi>Strand,</hi> &amp;c. He brings in this Story of the bringing in of <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery</hi> into <hi>England;</hi> the Arch-biſhop <hi>Cranmer</hi> ſent for <hi>Martin Bucer</hi> and <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> who were more addicted to the <hi>Zuinglian</hi> than the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Doctrines; the former was placed in the Doctor's Chair at <hi>Cambridge,</hi> holding correſpondency with <hi>Calvin,</hi> but ſoon died; but the latter, <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> in his Divinity Lectures at <hi>Oxford,</hi> declared himſelf a <hi>Zuinglian,</hi> and no faſt friend to Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, (I add this to Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi>) ſaying, [<hi>Ego, cum Canonicus</hi> Oxoniae <hi>eſſem, ſuper-polliceis uti non auderem;</hi>] I, while Canon of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Church in <hi>Oxford,</hi> durſt not wear a Surplice But the Dr. proceeds in his Story, how much the <hi>Zuinglian</hi> Goſpellers were againſt the <hi>Book of Homilies,</hi> &amp;c. and how Dr. <hi>Hooper,</hi> being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> refuſed to be conſecrated by Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop <hi>Cranmer</hi> in ſuch Habits as Biſhops are required to wear by the Rules of the Church, which Refuſal put a ſtop to his Conſecration; but he, repairing to his Patron the Earl of <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick,</hi> obtained his Letter to the <hi>Arch biſhop,</hi> deſiring a forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of theſe Habits; adding alſo that it was the <hi>King</hi>'s deſire as well as his own; and requeſted farther, that he would not charge <hi>him</hi> with any Oath burthenſome to his Conſcience, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Oath of <hi>Canonical Obedience:</hi> yea, the <hi>King</hi> likewiſe wrote to the ſame effect, and ſo the matter was compoſed with ſome
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51818:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> moderation. Thus Dr. <hi>Heylin.</hi> And many more <hi>Non-conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> the Dr. complains of too long to rehearſe</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="remark">
                  <p>The fourth <hi>Remark</hi> is, the Hiſtory of <hi>Non-conformity</hi> in Q. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeth</hi>'s Reign, who had bravely repulſed Temptations of tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Papiſt in Q. <hi>Mary</hi>'s time, with ſaying, [<hi>My Soul is the Lord's,</hi> and <hi>as to my Faith, as I cannot change it, ſo neither will I diſſemble it.</hi>] This good Queen, finding all the Land lay fallow and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-grown with the Brambles of her Siſter's Popery, was forced to this Reſolve, <hi>Not to reform all at once, but by little and little:</hi> This ſlow progreſs therein brought up and introduced a <hi>Medley</hi> of <hi>Calviniſts</hi> (as Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> ſtyles the <hi>Non-conformiſts</hi> at that time) in his <hi>Hiſt. of Reform.</hi> p 115. ſaying, Thoſe Miniſters that had been baniſh'd in the Reign of Q. <hi>Mary,</hi> and had followed (beyond Sea) the Platform of <hi>Geneva,</hi> returned ſo diſaffected to <hi>Epiſcopal Government,</hi> and to the <hi>Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> here by Law eſtabliſhed, as not long after filled the Church, as he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth it, with ſad Diſorders. On which account, he ſaith, we find the Queen's Profeſſor at <hi>Oxford</hi> to paſs among the <hi>Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts,</hi> though ſomewhat more moderate than the reſt; and <hi>Cartwright</hi> at <hi>Cambridge</hi> (he doth not call him Doctor, nor ſo much as Maſter <hi>Cartwright</hi>) who proved, ſaith he, an unextin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhable Fire brand to the <hi>Church of England:</hi> beſide him, there was <hi>Whittington</hi> (the chief Ring-leader of the <hi>Frankford</hi> Schiſmaticks) preferred to the Deanry of <hi>Durham,</hi> and from thence encouraging <hi>Knox</hi> and <hi>Goodman,</hi> in ſetting up <hi>Presbytery</hi> in the <hi>Kirk of Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Sampſon</hi> was advanced to the Deanry of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s-Church, but turned out again, for an incorrigible <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſt;</hi> as likewiſe <hi>Hardiman,</hi> one of the firſt twelve Prebends of the Church of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> who was ſoon after deprived, for throwing down the Altar and defacing the Veſtments of the Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="remark">
                  <p>The fifth <hi>Remark,</hi> Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> proceeds in his Complaints, <hi>pag.</hi> 124. ſaying, The <hi>Queen</hi> having ſetled <hi>Eccleſiaſtick Affairs,</hi> the ſame Settlement of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> might have longer continued, had not her Order been Confounded by ſome Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Spirits (as he calls them,) who, having had their Wills at <hi>Frankfort,</hi> or otherwiſe Ruling the <hi>Presbytery</hi> when they were at <hi>Geneva,</hi> thought to have carry'd all before them with the like facility when they were in <hi>England.</hi> And again, <hi>pag.</hi> 131, 132. Some friends they had about the Queen, and <hi>Calvin</hi> was Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51818:7"/> to make uſe of all his Power both with the Queen and with <hi>Cecill</hi> (as appears by his Letters to both) to Advance their Ends; and he was ſeconded by <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> who thought his Intereſt in <hi>England</hi> to be greater than <hi>Calvin</hi>'s, though his Name was not ſo eminent in other places; but the Queen had fixed her ſelf to keep up ſome outward Splendour of a Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> No ſooner thoſe Schiſmaticks of <hi>Frankfort</hi> ſaw <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> ſetled and the <hi>Liturgy</hi> impos'd, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but they Revive the quarrels rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in King <hi>Edward</hi>'s time, <hi>&amp;c. Grindal</hi> the new <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> was known to have a great Reſpect for <hi>Calvin</hi> and they two, by the help of their friends they had about the Queen, got liberty for a <hi>French Church,</hi> as <hi>John Alaſco</hi> had in King <hi>Edward</hi>'s time: But what was this (ſaith he) but ſetting up <hi>Presbytery</hi> to confront <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and a <hi>Common-wealth</hi> in the midſt of a <hi>Monarchy,</hi> or (as the phraſe is now) <hi>Imperium in Imperio. Calvin</hi> gives <hi>Grindal</hi> thanks for this favour, upon which many <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> repaired into <hi>England,</hi> planted themſelves in Sea-Towns, as well as in <hi>London</hi> openly profeſſing the Reformed Religion. Again, <hi>pag.</hi> 144 he goes on, ſaying, Now nothing would ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie our <hi>Non-conformiſts</hi> at Home, (being thus encourag'd with that liberty thus procured for thoſe abroad) but the <hi>Nakedneſs</hi> and <hi>Simplicity</hi> of the <hi>Zuinglian Churches,</hi> the new faſhions taken up at <hi>Frankfort,</hi> and the <hi>Presbyteries</hi> at <hi>Geneva;</hi> and they drove on ſo faſt upon it, that they took down the Steps where the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar ſtood, and brought the Table into the midſt of the Church in ſome places; they laid aſide <hi>God fathers</hi> and <hi>God-mothers</hi> in <hi>Baptiſm;</hi> and <hi>Lent</hi> they look'd upon as Superſtition and <hi>Feſtival</hi> days, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This Faction (ſaith he <hi>pag.</hi> 154) could not touch <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> nor <hi>Liturgy,</hi> becauſe eſtabliſhed by Law; but <hi>Caps, Tippets, Rochets, Lawn-ſleeves</hi> and <hi>Surplices,</hi> &amp;c (all having no better foundation than Superſritious Cuſtom, or ſome old Popiſh Canon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) they Aſſaulted: And when the book of the <hi>Thirty-nine Articles</hi> was publiſh'd, they boggl'd at the <hi>Twentieth</hi> about the Authority of the Church, and at the <hi>Thirty-ſixth</hi> about the Conſecration of <hi>Arch-biſhops,</hi> &amp;c. the book of <hi>Homilies</hi> they call'd <hi>beggarly Rudiments,</hi> and other things not conſiſting with their <hi>Independency.</hi> The Doctor proceeds, [<hi>Of this factions Number,</hi> none ſo much Remarkable, as Father <hi>John Fox</hi> the <hi>Martyrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſt,</hi> &amp;c.] it was thought by the <hi>Conformiſts</hi> that the Opinion
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51818:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> which was had of his <hi>Parts</hi> and <hi>Piety</hi> might much Advance <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity,</hi> if the Heads of the Church could cauſe him to come over to them and <hi>ſubſcribe</hi> the <hi>Thirty-nine</hi> Articles; hereupon he was Summon'd for his <hi>Subſcription:</hi> He appear'd before the Biſhop with his New-Teſtament in Greek, holding it in his hand, he ſaid, [<hi>Unto this book I will Subſcribe; and if this will not Serve, take my Prebendary at</hi> Salisbury, <hi>the only Preferment which I hold in the Church of</hi> England, <hi>and much good may it doe you.</hi>] But notwithſtanding this Refractory Anſwer (ſaith the Doctor) ſo much kindneſs was ſhewed to him, that he both kept his <hi>Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution,</hi> and his <hi>Prebendary</hi> together: This was more favour than is ſhewn to any <hi>Non-conformiſt</hi> in this our Days. And to this the Doctor adds, That thoſe <hi>Genevians</hi> (as he ſtyles them) for the greater Countenancing of their <hi>Non-conformity,</hi> ſtirred up the moſt <hi>Eminent Divines</hi> of the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Zuinglian</hi> or <hi>Helve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian Churches</hi> to Declare in favour of their Doings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="remark">
                  <p>The ſixth <hi>Remark</hi> is, the Doctor tells us many long Stories, too large to tranſcribe. After his Invectives againſt the <hi>Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans,</hi> ſo called (he ſaith) for pretending to a greater Purity in God's Worſhip, and againſt <hi>Geneva Notes</hi> upon 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 8.15, 16, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and againſt the Sawcineſs of <hi>Knox,</hi> and the bold Activities of <hi>Beza</hi> for upholding this <hi>Puritan Faction.</hi> He comes to <hi>Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright,</hi> againſt whom he exclaims for ſowing his Seed of <hi>Non-conformity</hi> in <hi>Cambridge</hi> it ſelf, and ſo that it could never be Rooted out to this Day. Who exceeded (he ſaith) in Acting more than any of the <hi>Puritan Faction:</hi> He preached All the Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows and Scholars of his Colledge out of their Surplices, <hi>&amp;c. Heylin</hi>'s Hiſt. of <hi>Presbytery,</hi> pag. 263. He ſet up a Presbyterial Church at <hi>Wandſworth</hi> by the Water ſide, near <hi>London, Novemb.</hi> 20. in the Year 1572. He introduced his <hi>Diſcipline</hi> into the Iſlands of <hi>Jerſey</hi> and <hi>Gernſey,</hi> and in the <hi>Engliſh Church</hi> at <hi>Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleburgh</hi> in <hi>Zealand,</hi> and in the <hi>Dutch Church</hi> here in <hi>London;</hi> yea he prevailed ſo far (with the Aſſiſtance of the Earl of <hi>Leice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> Lord-Treaſurer <hi>Burleigh,</hi> &amp;c.) that a Meeting of Sixty Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters out of <hi>Eſſex, Cambridge</hi> and <hi>Norfolk</hi> was Held at <hi>Cork<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill.</hi> where <hi>Knewſtubbs</hi> was Miniſter, <hi>May</hi> the 8th. in the Year 1582. and the like Meeting was Held at <hi>Cambridge,</hi> &amp;c. After this (ſaith he) their book of <hi>Diſcipline</hi> being publiſhed, was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where more welcom than in <hi>London,</hi> the Wealth and Pride of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51818:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> which City was never wanting to ſupport ſuch, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> pag. 213. The ſeveral Churches they had in the City they Reduced into one general <hi>Claſſis,</hi> in which either <hi>Cartwright,</hi> or <hi>Egerton,</hi> or <hi>Travers</hi> were for the moſt part <hi>Moderatours.</hi> This was their chief Tribunal and ſupreme Conſiſtory they held for the whole Nation: But in the Country none appear'd more forward, than thoſe of <hi>Northampton, Daventry</hi> and <hi>Nottingham</hi> and the <hi>Device</hi> (as he calls it) is taken up in moſt parts of <hi>England,</hi> but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in <hi>Warwick-ſhire, Suffolk, Norfolk, Eſſex,</hi> &amp;c. In theſe Claſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes they Determined Points of Doctrine, Interpreted hard pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Scripture, Delivered their Reſolution in ſuch Caſes of Conſcience, as were brought before them; Decided Doubts and Difficulties touching <hi>Contracts of Marriage,</hi> &amp;c. And whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever was coucluded by ſuch as were preſent, (yet ſtill with Reference to the better Judgment of their <hi>London-brethren</hi>) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came forthwith binding to the Reſt; none being admitted into any of the aforeſaid <hi>Claſſes</hi> before he had promiſed under his Hand, that he would Submit himſelf, and be Obedient unto all ſuch <hi>Orders</hi> and <hi>Decrees,</hi> as were ſet down by the <hi>Claſſis</hi> to be obſerved. At theſe <hi>Claſſes</hi> they enquired into the Life and Doctrine of all that had ſubſcribed unto them, <hi>Cenſuring</hi> ſome, and <hi>Depoſing</hi> others as they ſaw occaſion. Unto every <hi>Claſſis</hi> there belonged a <hi>Regiſter,</hi> who took the Heads of all that paſſed, and ſaw them carefully entred into a Book for that purpoſe, that they might remain upon Record. This is Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation in full of the progreſs of <hi>Presbytery</hi> in this Nation.</p>
                  <p>Moreover, Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> obſerves that in Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s 7th. Year of her Reign, the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> began firſt to be called <hi>Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans;</hi> and in her 8th Year the Government of the Church by <hi>Arch-biſhops</hi> and <hi>Biſhops</hi> was Confirmed, which when the <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians</hi> ſaw ſetled, they began (ſaith he) to play their Game; and the more, becauſe the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> prevailed now in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have been the larger in Quoting Dr. <hi>Heylin,</hi> becauſe the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of an Adverſary [to <hi>Non-conformiſts</hi>] is always look'd upon as a double, and ſo the ſtrongeſt Teſtimony.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="remark">
                  <p>The ſeventh <hi>Remark</hi> take here in few words. Sir <hi>Richard Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi>'s Teſtimony alſo, who ſaith, That in the <hi>Eleventh</hi> Year of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51818:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Reign there aroſe a Sect, openly Condemning the Received Diſcipline of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> together with the <hi>Church Liturgy</hi> and the very Calling of <hi>Biſhops.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This Sect (ſaith <hi>Baker</hi>) ſo mightily encreaſed, that in the Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Year of her Reign the <hi>Queen</hi> and whole Kingdom were extreamly troubled with them: And again, in a <hi>Parliament</hi> held the 26th Year of her Reign, the <hi>Puritan Party</hi> laboured to have Laws made in order to the Deſtroying of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and the ſetting up of their own Sect: And again, in her 28th Year the Queen gave a Special Charge to <hi>Whitgiſt,</hi> Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> to ſettle an Uniformity in the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline,</hi> which now almoſt lay a gaſping; and at this time the Sect of <hi>Browniſts</hi> (derived from one <hi>Robert Brown,</hi> who Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niz'd the moſt Rigid ſort of Separation from the Church of <hi>England</hi>) did much oppoſe the <hi>National Church.</hi> Again, in her <hi>One and Thirtieth Year,</hi> the <hi>Puritan flames</hi> brake forth again; and in her Thirty-ſixth Year the ſeverity of the Laws were executed upon <hi>Henry Barrow</hi> and his <hi>Sectaries</hi> for Condemning the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> as no Chriſtian Church. Thus Sir <hi>Richard Baker,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="remark">
                  <p>The eighth <hi>Remark</hi> is, This <hi>Severity</hi> of the <hi>Conformiſts</hi> againſt the <hi>Non-conformiſts</hi> in Depriving them of their <hi>Benefices</hi> and other Preferments in the Church, (beſide their later Cruelty to them) went as Alarming news, flying both into <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Scotland.</hi> Hereupon (ſaith Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> in his Hiſtory of <hi>Presbytery,</hi> pag. 252.) both <hi>Beza</hi> out of <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Knox</hi> with his <hi>Comrades</hi> out of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> interpoſe themſelves in behalf of their Brethren: As to <hi>Knox</hi> (ſaith he) a Letter was wrote by him and ſent in the Name of the <hi>General Aſſembly</hi> of the <hi>Kirk</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> wherein the Church-Veſtments are call'd Trifles and <hi>Rags of Rome,</hi> &amp;c. But <hi>Beza</hi> (ſaith he) writes with more Authority from <hi>France,</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the greater <hi>Patriarch,</hi> unto <hi>Grindal</hi> of greater Matters than <hi>Caps</hi> and <hi>Surplices,</hi> but complains of Suſpending theſe Men from their Miniſtry for not Subſcribing to ſome new Ceremonies impos'd upon them, and that the <hi>Biſhops</hi> had too much power, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts againſt many other things. So good a foundation (ſaith he) being laid, the Building could not chuſe but go on a-pace. In the Courſe of which Fabrick, they have continually a Recourſe to this <hi>Beza,</hi> as to their Maſter Workman, anſwering all their Scruples
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51818:9"/> And the Dr. adds, the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> had many powerful Friends at Court, as the Earl of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> Lord <hi>North, Knolls,</hi> and <hi>Walſingham,</hi> which ſo encourag'd them, that they met together in <hi>Houſes, Woods, Barns,</hi> and <hi>common Fields,</hi> where they <hi>kept</hi> their <hi>Conventicles,</hi> pag. 252, 259, 262, 263. until at laſt (ſaith he pag. 271.) They reſolved againſt the Epiſcopal, and endeavour'd to erect the <hi>Presbyterial</hi> Government, concluding their Vote thus, <q rend="inline">[Whereas divers Books have been writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and ſundry Petitions have been exhibited to her Majeſty, the Parliament and their Lordſhips to little purpoſe, every man ſhould therefore labour by all means poſſible, to bring the Reformation into the Church] and 'twas then and there reſolved, [That for the better bringing on of the ſaid <hi>Holy Diſcipline,</hi> they ſhould not only as well publickly as privately teach it, but alſo by little and little as well as poſſible they could, draw the ſame into practice.]</q> Hereupon a <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery</hi> was erected at that ſmall Village in <hi>Surry</hi> called <hi>Wandsworth,</hi> as is aforeſaid, and <hi>Grindal</hi> being tranſlated from the See of <hi>York</hi> unto that of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> gave great hopes to the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> who ſoon found how plyant he was like to prove unto their expectation, which happen'd accordingly, for he ſought in all things to promote their Deſigns, and made great Alterations in the <hi>Church of England,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="remark">
                  <p>
                     <hi>The 8th. Remark.</hi> The <hi>Commiſſaries</hi> Court, that had been ſo ſevere againſt the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> all along began to learn more mildneſs in the latter end of Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Reign, as appeareth by that inſtance of Mr. <hi>Richard Sedgwick,</hi> the Miniſter at <hi>Batterſey</hi> in <hi>Surry,</hi> who was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted by one Mr. <hi>King</hi> Churchwarden of the place, and was preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by him into the <hi>Biſhops Court,</hi> and cited to anſwer there the Articles he had to object againſt him, principally for his exclaiming againſt thoſe Corruptions that then were in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> the good Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter couragiouſly appeared, to defend what he had preached; but ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing before the <hi>Commiſſary,</hi> beyond his expectation, he me with courteous Uſage, and was friendly diſmiſſed; The Reaſon is rendred, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thoſe kind of high flown perſecuting <hi>Conformiſts</hi> feared ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable change to be brought in by K. <hi>James</hi>'s coming to the Crown, who had been train'd up by the <hi>Kirk of Scotland</hi> in the <hi>Presbyterial</hi> way: See Mr. <hi>Rich. Sedgwick</hi>'s Life writ by Mr. <hi>Clark, pag.</hi> 397. in <hi>Fol.</hi> N. B. Thus might I carry on this Hiſtory of <hi>Nonconfermity,</hi> both through K. <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, and K. <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, yea, and <hi>Charle:</hi> the Second, and <hi>James</hi> the Second; but this would make a Volume
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51818:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> All that can be contain'd here, is the Hiſtory of the <hi>Infancy</hi> of it in the firſt Reformers.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <div n="1" type="remark">
                  <head>Remark 1ſt.</head>
                  <p>UPon K. <hi>James</hi>'s Reign in the year 1605. at <hi>Hamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton-Court,</hi> he calls an <hi>Aſſembly of Divines</hi> to confer about the <hi>Liturgy</hi> and <hi>Church Government,</hi> where he told them, that his End of calling them together was not to make any Alteration, which was not requiſite, ſeeing he found all things ſo well ſetled al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, but like a wiſe <hi>Phyſician,</hi> he would ſearch into the ſuppoſed Diſeaſes, and remove the occaſion of Complaints, whereupon the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates of his Privy Council were diſmiſſed, and the <hi>Monday</hi> after he calls in the complaining <hi>Doctors,</hi> telling them, he meant not to alter the <hi>Church Government,</hi> ſo well ſetled already, but to ſettle <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity</hi> and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> &amp;c. Dr. <hi>Reynolds</hi> the Foreman, reduceth their Grievances to theſe four Heads. Firſt, For <hi>preſerving true Doctrine.</hi> Secondly, <hi>For placing Good Paſtors.</hi> Thirdly, For ſincere <hi>Church-Government.</hi> And, Fourthly, For explaining ſome paſſages in the <hi>Service-Book.</hi> Of this <hi>Conference,</hi> &amp;c. I muſt refer my Reader to Mr. <hi>Fuller</hi>'s <hi>Church Hiſtory,</hi> who (according to his Name,) gives a <hi>fuller</hi> Account, than this ſmall Treatiſe is capable of: Some brief touches make,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="remark">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Remark the Second.</hi> Mr. <hi>Fuller</hi> ſaith, that Dr. <hi>Barlow,</hi> (then an oppoſite to the <hi>Nonconformiſts,</hi>) doth not give an impartial Relation of this Conference: Whereupon he wittily ſaith, If the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> be forced to whet their Tools with the <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> no wonder if the <hi>Thiliſtims</hi> ſet a ſharper edge on their own, and a blunter upon their enemies <hi>Weapons,</hi> he was a <hi>Party</hi> and ſo was <hi>partial</hi> in favouring the <hi>Conformiſts,</hi> &amp;c. But Mr. <hi>Fuller.</hi> Cent 17. Book 10. pag. 21. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Saith, here was great <hi>odds;</hi> only theſe four (<hi>Reinolds, Knewſtubbs, Spark,</hi> and <hi>Chaderton,</hi>) called to cope with 8 Biſhops, 8 Deans, and two Doctors, beſide the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Privy Council:</hi> Nor were they called to have their Scruples ſatisfyed, but his Pleaſure pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded; the King call'd them not, that he might know what they could ſay, but that they might know what he would do in the matter. For tho they petition'd for a full Reformation of <hi>Church-Service,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:51818:10"/> Livings, Miniſters,</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> and that with a Millena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Petition,</hi> ſubſcribed with about <hi>a thouſand Miniſters hands,</hi> yet got they not the Kings Ear, but he cryed to them [<hi>No Biſhop no King, and as they dealt with my mother, ſo would they deal with me. I'le make you conform, or baniſh you,</hi> &amp;c.] But he order'd a new Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation of the Bible (differing from that of <hi>Geneva,</hi>) charging the Tranſlators to keep the old Eccleſiaſtick words, as <hi>Church</hi> and not <hi>Congregation,</hi> and <hi>Eaſter,</hi> &amp;c. and not to make any <hi>marginal Notes</hi> as were in the <hi>Geneva Bibles,</hi> againſt which he much exclaimed, and more eſpecially its <hi>Notes</hi> upon <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.19. which allows Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Kings; and on 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.16. ſaying, <hi>Aſa</hi> ſhould have <hi>kill'd the Queen,</hi> and not <hi>depoſed</hi> her only.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="remark">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Remark the Third.</hi> Mr. <hi>Fuller</hi> ſays further, when Dr. <hi>Reynolds</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> complaining againſt <hi>Arminian Doctrine,</hi> lazy Miniſters bad Gover<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of the Church and Common Prayer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſaying, It was t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> cry of the People, Such a <hi>Church,</hi> &amp;c. will bring the Souls of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Nation into a faint and feeble condition, having no warm meet pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vided for them, ſave only the <hi>cold Homilies,</hi> and the <hi>Starve-us-Book,</hi> &amp;<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Biſhop <hi>Bancroft</hi> at this <hi>Hampton-Court</hi> Conference, anſwered only with urging that old Canon (<hi>Schiſmatici contra Epiſcopos non ſunt au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diendi,</hi>) Schiſmaticks ought not to be heard in their complaining a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Biſhops, and ſaid, He was beholden to the King to ſuffer him thus to ſpeak againſt the <hi>Laturgy,</hi> contrary to the Statute in the firſt year of Q. <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> and that probably he was of the ſame mind with Mr. <hi>Cartwright,</hi> who would conform in Ceremonie, rather to the <hi>Turks,</hi> than to the Papiſts. Book. 10. pag 11. Cent. 17. And the ſame Biſhop <hi>Bancroft</hi> bade K. <hi>James</hi> remember the Speech of the <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſador <hi>Rognee,</hi> who ſaid, That if the Reformed Church in <hi>France</hi> had kept the ſame Order both in <hi>Service</hi> and in <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> there would have been a thouſand more <hi>Proteſtants</hi> than there be in that Land, intimating, That if the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> there had embraced the ſame <hi>Service</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> with the <hi>Prelates</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> (which they could not do, but differed from them,) the <hi>Popiſh Party</hi> in <hi>France</hi> would have been pleaſed with them; and their <hi>Conformity</hi> would have preven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed the <hi>Pariſian Maſſac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e. pag.</hi> 15. The ſame Biſhop ſaid likewiſe, That in a Church newly planted, <hi>Preaching</hi> is moſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; but it is not ſo in a Church long eſtabliſhed as ours is, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by his Deſign was to thruſt out <hi>Sermons</hi> as unneceſſary, by the more neceſſary <hi>Service-Book pag.</hi> 15.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="remark">
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:51818:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Remark the Fourth</hi> But the Lord <hi>Chancellor</hi> ſaid at that ſame <hi>Hamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton Court Conference,</hi> that Church-Livings at that time wanted rather <hi>Learned-men,</hi> than Learned men any Church livings. Many ſuch pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for want of Places through their <hi>Nonconformity;</hi> and to this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint he added, That he wiſhed every Learned man were ſupplyed with a <hi>ſingle Coat,</hi> to wit, <hi>one Church-Benefice,</hi> before that others be thatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on with double and treble Coats, in their <hi>Pluralities,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 16. Mr. <hi>Knewſtubb</hi> the <hi>Nonconformiſt</hi> at the ſame Conference ſaid, <q rend="inline">(Put the caſe, That the Church hath Power to add any ſignificant Signs, it may not add them where <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath already ordered them. This derogates from the Authority of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as much as if any ſhould preſume to add any thing to the <hi>Great Seal of England,</hi> &amp;c.)</q> Theſe few inſtances I have inſerted in this ſmall Tract out of Mr. <hi>Fuller,</hi> who was a famous <hi>Epiſcopal Divine,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="remark">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Remark the Fifth.</hi> Tho King <hi>James</hi> was look'd upon by the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates,</hi> as no better than an <hi>Arrant Puritan,</hi> when he came firſt to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> and was the firſt King that ever was proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed K. of <hi>Great Britain, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> yet <hi>Cluverius</hi> teſtifies of him, That he left the <hi>Church of England</hi> as he found it at the Death of Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> without any Reformation or Redreſs of Grievances therein; inſomuch, that ſome (ſeverely enough) deſcribing his Court and Character, diſcover much of his <hi>King craft,</hi> even ſuch as were Eye witneſſes, or Ear-witneſſes thereof, and ſo making good his own Motto (<hi>Qui neſcit diſſimulare, neſcit Regnare,</hi>) He that cannot Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble ought not to Reign. Mr. <hi>Fuller</hi> tells us, That in his time Archbiſhop <hi>Abbot</hi>'s ſtiffneſs about the Earl of <hi>Eſſex</hi>'s Divorce, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> though it was to his eternal Honour in not complying with the <hi>Bawdy Biſhops,</hi> yet the King and Court were his Foes for it ever after; and above all, Biſhop <hi>Laud</hi> (whom he calls <hi>Filius ante diem,</hi>) ſets himſelf againſt him, and as if not content to ſucceed him, he endeavour'd to ſupplant him, as if a falling Tree ſtood in need of felling, he being now exceeding old. <hi>Fuller. Ch. Hiſt. Cent.</hi> 17. <hi>B.</hi> 11. <hi>p.</hi> 128.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <div n="1" type="remark">
                  <p>BUt leaving K. <hi>James,</hi> as he leſt his Throne to K. <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, a few <hi>Remarks</hi> upon his Reign: As, Firſt, Mr. <hi>Fuller</hi> tells us, how Biſhop <hi>Laud</hi> (that grand Maſter of Ceremonies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) had
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:51818:11"/> entred into his <hi>Diary,</hi> that the <hi>Parliament</hi> in the fourth year of <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, <hi>Anno Dom</hi> 1628. did earr eſtly endeavour his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. <hi>Cent.</hi> 17. <hi>Book</hi> 11. <hi>pag.</hi> 132. In which <hi>Parliament</hi> Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> charges Dr. <hi>Manwaring</hi> that he taught (The <hi>Conſciences</hi> of <hi>Subjects are bound to obey illegal Commands,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>yea, and damns them in caſe of Diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience,</hi> &amp;c.) Relating likewiſe, how Dr. <hi>Cozens</hi> ſet up in <hi>Durham</hi> a marble Altar with <hi>Cherabims,</hi> which coſt Two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Pound, and he made a Gaudy <hi>Cope</hi> with the <hi>Trinity</hi> Embroider'd upon it, whereon was God the Father in the figure of an Old Man, and another with a <hi>Crucifix</hi> and <hi>Chriſts</hi> In age having a Red Beard, and a Blew Cap upon his Head, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And how this ſame Dr. lighted two hundred Wax Candles about his Altar upon <hi>Candlemaſs-Day:</hi> And how he forbad ſinging of <hi>Pſalms,</hi> but Commanded <hi>Anthems</hi> to be Sung, and among the Reſt, an <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>them</hi> of the three <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>Colain, Gaſpar, Belthazar,</hi> and <hi>Mclchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, &amp;c.</hi> And how this Dr. procured a Conſecrated Knife wherewith to cut his <hi>Sacrament Bread,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ibidem.</hi> pag. 173.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="remark">
                  <p>
                     <hi>The 2d. Remark.</hi> Is that of Mr. <hi>Fuller's</hi> ſaying, thoſe high <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates</hi> call (the Bp. of <hi>Armagh.</hi> Dr. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> D. <hi>Morton,</hi> Dr. <hi>Hall,</hi> Dr. <hi>Sanders,</hi> Dr. <hi>Brownrigg,</hi> Dr. <hi>Holdſworth,</hi>) all thoſe famous <hi>Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,</hi> a Company of <hi>Puritanical Biſhops,</hi> that were <hi>Doctrinal,</hi> tho' not <hi>Diſciplinary Puritans,</hi> who ſaid that the Doctrine of the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of Trent,</hi> was preached by theſe <hi>Biſhops. Fuller.</hi> Ch. Hiſt. pag. 174.175.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="remark">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Remark</hi> the third. Mr. <hi>Fuller</hi> relateth how the grievances of <hi>Arch-Biſhop Williams</hi> did much haſten, if not chiefly cauſe the Suppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that Eccleſiaſtick Court, the <hi>Star Chamber,</hi> the two Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops being therein engaged againſt each other, <hi>pag.</hi> 159. and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe how the <hi>Convocation</hi> in the Year 1640. had full Commiſſion from King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>1ſt.</hi> either to alter the old Canons, or to make new ones; which Royal Power had not been granted for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Years before. <hi>Fuller, ibidem.</hi> pag. 168. And how (after that Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was diſſolved) the <hi>Convocation</hi> ſtill ſate, wherem to fewer than thirty ſix of themſelves were <hi>Diſſenters</hi> among them; but their Oath obliged them, that none ſhould ever give conſent to the altering of the <hi>Church Government;</hi> which Oath ſeemed to Abridge the Liberty and Authority of both <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament,</hi> who had a power of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration when they ſaw cauſe for it. Beſide, this Oath (<hi>ſaith he</hi>) had
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51818:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                     <hi>a Windy,,</hi> [<hi>Et caetera</hi>] in it, a <hi>Cheverel word,</hi> which like a <hi>Cheverel point,</hi> might be ſtretched out at pleaſure: This ſame figure [<hi>&amp;c.</hi>] in the Oath, the Witty Poet <hi>Cleveland</hi> (my Contemporary in the Univerſity) call'd the <hi>Curled Lock</hi> of <hi>Anti-Chriſt:</hi> And tho time was given for Conforming to this (<hi>Et caetera Oath</hi>) until the twenty ninth of <hi>September,</hi> to deliberate upon it, yet ſome over active Biſhops (ſaith Mr. <hi>Fuller</hi>) did preſently preſs the Oath upon ſome Miniſters, yea, and to take this <hi>Biſhop's</hi> Oath kneeling, which is a Ceremony (ſaith he) that is never exacted nor obſerved in taking the Oath of Allegiance and Supremacy to the King. <hi>pag.</hi> 171. And how Dr. <hi>Turner</hi> in his Convocation Sermon blamed ſome Biſhops for their being too meek and moderate, and bidding them, that with equal ſtrictneſs they would preſs forward an <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Conformity:</hi> And indeed they did as he bad them, puſhing End-ways this matter of Conformity, until they ſet all the Kingdom into a Flame, in the late Civil <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncivil Wars, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="remark">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Remark the Fourth.</hi> By all the aforeſaid (tho' it be not the Tenth part of what Mr. <hi>Fuller</hi> ſaith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) It cannet be wordred at, that ſo many <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> (both of the <hi>Presbyterial</hi> and <hi>Congregational</hi> Judgment) have ſeparated themſelves from ſuch a <hi>Church of England,</hi> ſo Characterized not only by Dr. <hi>Ames,</hi> in his freſh ſuit againſt Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies; and Mr. <hi>Robinſons</hi> Juſtification of a ſeparation from the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and the Remonſtrance of Mr. <hi>Cartwright</hi> Subſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by a thouſand <hi>Miniſters</hi> here in <hi>England;</hi> beſide <hi>Zarchy</hi>'s Epiſtle to the Queen at large, all which and many more Authors of that Subject I have by me: To ſay nothing of <hi>Calvin, Beza, &amp;c.</hi> This Mr. <hi>Fuller</hi> being an <hi>Epiſcopal Divine,</hi> tells Tales enow out of his Church, for which doing, he could riſe no higher than a poor <hi>Preb n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary.</hi> Let him be <hi>Inſtar omnium,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="remark">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Remark the Fifth.</hi> If any enquire more after the particular Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> Separation from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> take this brief Account as this Tract will admit of, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div n="1" type="reason">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Reaſon the 1ſt.</hi> Upon the ſame ground that the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſeparateth from <hi>Rome,</hi> do we ſeparate from them. Dr. <hi>Stillingſteet</hi> in his <hi>Dialogue</hi> for juſtifying their <hi>Separation</hi> from <hi>home,</hi> ſaith, <hi>pag.</hi> 165. [<hi>We think the Requiring of doubtful things for certain, falſe for true,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:51818:12"/> new for old, abſurd for Reaſonable, is ground enough for us not to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace communion with that Church, unleſs it may be had upon better terms.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Now let the Mouth of this battering Cannon be but turn'd againſt the <hi>Church of England,</hi> as 'tis there againſt the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> it will aſſuredly give as loud a Report, and do as much Execution for us in juſtifying our Separation as well as theirs; Seeing there are Impoſed on us, <hi>Doubtful things for certain,</hi> &amp;c. And we think this is <hi>ground enough</hi> for us, as well as for themſelves, not to Embrace the Communion of ſuch a Church: Why may not our (<hi>we think ſo</hi>) be as good as their (<hi>we think ſo?</hi>) Why may not our <hi>Rouland</hi> be as good as their <hi>Oliver?</hi> What is good <hi>Sawce</hi> for a <hi>Gooſe,</hi> may be as <hi>good Sawce</hi> for a <hi>Gander,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="reason">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Reaſon the 2d.</hi> A Compariſon betwixt the <hi>Primitive</hi> and the <hi>Preſent Engliſh Church:</hi> The <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> find a great many <hi>Humane Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> in the latter, that were never Divine Inſtitutions in the former; <hi>Such as</hi> Cathedral Muſick, <hi>with</hi> Organs, Chancellours, Commiſſaries, Officials, <hi>Pompous Prelates, with ſole Power of Ordination and Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, Calling of Miniſters without the expreſs conſent of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, over which they are placed; Miniſters going to Law for their Places, Pluralities, Non Reſidents, Dumb Curates Simony, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Contemners of Religion made Members of the Church; Carnal proceedings in Spiritual Courts; Bribes for Ordinations, Citations, Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions, and many more ſuch Additionals of the ſame Brann, whereof there was not the leaſt ſhew or ſhadow allowed in the Primitive Church</hi>
                        <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Now the <hi>Noncons</hi> Argue with their Lord and Maſter, [<hi>Non erat ſic ab initio, nec ab inſtituto</hi>] It was not ſo from the Beginning, nor <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Inſtitution, therefore our [<hi>we think</hi>] ſteps higher into [<hi>We are ſure</hi>] Such <hi>Deviſed Ceremonies</hi> as <hi>Surplice, Croſſing, Kneeling,</hi> &amp;c, ought not to be Embraced, having none of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Mark, but rather of <hi>Anti Chriſt</hi>'s upon them, 'tis a <hi>Symbolizing with Rome,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="reason">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Reaſon the 3d.</hi> A free <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſent</hi> cannot be given to ſuch <hi>Innovations</hi> wherewith the meer <hi>Prudentials</hi> of Byaſſed-Church Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours have ſpoiled the <hi>naked Truth,</hi> and ſimplicity of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel. What was it but Humane <hi>Prudence</hi> in thoſe Corrupter times ſucceeding the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> that formed new Churches, new Officers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Wholly differing from thoſe Inſtituted by <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles;</hi>
                        <pb n="22" facs="tcp:51818:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> for then it was pretended, that to keep Peace among the <hi>Paſtors</hi> of particular Churches, they deviſed a <hi>Biſhop</hi> to be ſet over them, and to keep the <hi>Biſhops</hi> from falling together by the Ears, they Invented an <hi>Arch-Biſhop,</hi> and becauſe thoſe <hi>Metropolitans</hi> might poſſibly quarrel, they found out a <hi>Patriarch</hi> to keep them in peace; and laſtly, becauſe <hi>Patriarchs</hi> were ſubject to the ſame Paſſions with other Men, they from the like Prudentials Inſtituted a <hi>Pope,</hi> and placed him in the Infallible Chair, to overtop them all, and to Hec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor them with his Bulls into a <hi>due Decorum.</hi> The ſame may be ſaid of all other unſcriptural Additions and <hi>Innovations</hi> in the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, both as to <hi>Service</hi> and as to <hi>Ceremony,</hi> &amp;c. Which we cannot have <hi>Faith</hi> for, being the <hi>Devices</hi> of <hi>Men,</hi> and not the <hi>Appointments</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> Now <hi>without Faith 'tis impoſſible to pleaſe God,</hi> Heb. 11.6. and <hi>whatever is not of Faith is Sin.</hi> Rom. 14.23. We may not offer to God, what we think will diſpleaſe him, and is a ſin againſt him.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="reason">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Reaſon the 4th.</hi> The Law of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> commanded by God to be the Temper and Character of the True Church, is by the Church of <hi>England</hi> changed into a Law of Uncharitable Compulſion, <hi>Severity,</hi> and <hi>Perſecution,</hi> which are evermore the Marks of the <hi>falſe Church;</hi> as of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which by their miſchievous Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions upon the Conſciences of Men, their meer Pretenſions, hath filled moſt Nations of <hi>Europe</hi> with Bloody Maſſacres and Martyrdom. Ten times more Blood of the tendereſt Chriſtians hath been ſhed by that <hi>falſe Church,</hi> than was ſhed in all the <hi>ten Primitive Pagan</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions: All that diſſent from them, may ſay, <hi>Quae Regio in Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris noſtri non plena Cruoris?</hi> Is there any Nation in <hi>Europe,</hi> that is not filled with our Blood? Now where-ever this Spirit of Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion turns up Trump, and is Regnant, Raging and Triumphant, there is <hi>like Mother, like Daughter,</hi> an <hi>Evil Spirit</hi> from the <hi>Devil</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that <hi>Envious</hi> and <hi>Evil one,</hi> the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Cain,</hi> who, (as <hi>Luther</hi> ſaith) will be clubbing his Brother <hi>Abel</hi> to the end of the World; 'tis the <hi>Spirit</hi> of a <hi>Phariſee</hi> that <hi>Compels Saints to Blaſpheme.</hi> Act. 26, 11. and ſaith to that <hi>See of Knowledge</hi> (which the Lord hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed <hi>ſhall fill the Earth as the Waters cover the Sea,</hi> Iſa. 11.9.) <hi>Toms far then ſhalt go in Conformity and no further,</hi> which is only God's Prerogative, <hi>Job</hi> 38.11. How can we give the Right-hand of Fellowſhip to ſuch a <hi>Perſecuting Church? &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:51818:13"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <div n="5" type="remark">
                  <div n="5" type="reason">
                     <p>
                        <hi>REaſon</hi> the Fifth. O here be too many High-flown Church-Men, that do aſſert <hi>Arminianiſm</hi> to be the <hi>Doctrin</hi> of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> thinking thereby to force all into an Embrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it: And ſome do hold up all <hi>Canons,</hi> not only made in <hi>England,</hi> but in <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf (if not repugnant to our Law)s labouring to poſſeſs the People, that all theſe are ſetled by Law, and therefore to be continued and impoſed without Alteration; and that all who ſeek a Reformation of them, do violate the Eſtabliſh'd Laws of the Land; as the Rigour of <hi>Conformity</hi> to thoſe <hi>Canons,</hi> did coſt the caſting forth of many able, godly and uſeful Miniſters, in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Reign, and of many more under King <hi>James,</hi> notwithſtanding the <hi>Conference</hi> at <hi>Hampton-Court;</hi> yet many Illegal Canons were made and Inforc'd ſo far to be ſubſcribed unto, that within the ſpace of two years, 70 worthy Miniſters were Deprived <hi>ab Officio &amp; Beneficio;</hi> and 113 were Suſpended and not ſuffered to Preach, and about 94 more were under <hi>Canonical Admonition,</hi> the next door to Deprivation. I need not add the horrible Effects which <hi>Canonical Obedience,</hi> and ſevere <hi>Conformity</hi> produced under the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, ſuch Confuſions as turn'd <hi>England</hi> into an <hi>Aceldama,</hi> a Field of Blood in the Civil Wars, abhorred to be mentioned, and trembled at to remember, wherein Father was againſt Son, and Son againſt Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        <q>
                           <l>—Quis talia fando</l>
                           <l>Temperet a Lachrymis?—</l>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>'Tis freſh in ſome of our Memories. Nor need I mention the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second when the black <hi>Bartholomew</hi> Act for Uniformity, turn'd out about three thouſand Miniſters from their Miniſtry, omitting the Exile of many Miniſters and People into <hi>America</hi> before: Many more Reaſons might be added, which this ſmall Tract is not capable to comprehend; I ſhall add only one more.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="reason">
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:51818:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Reaſon</hi> the Sixth. The great Growth of Popery hath been uſher'd in at this Door, as <hi>Adam Contzenus</hi> the <hi>Jeſuit</hi> directeth, for reſtoring Popery, before the People be awake: In his Politicks, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 16, 17, 18. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>His Sixth Rule is, to make uſe of the <hi>Proteſtant Diſſenſions,</hi> forcing the <hi>Puritans</hi> to approve of Biſhops, the Magiſtrate joyning with the <hi>Conformists,</hi> eaſily overturns the <hi>Nonconformists;</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> did by the Diſſention between the <hi>Phariſees</hi> and <hi>Sadducees,</hi> joyning to one Side, he eſcaped. Diſcords 'wixt <hi>Lutherans</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> 'twixt <hi>Arminians</hi> and <hi>Anti-Arminians,</hi> are the beſt Muſick to <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts.</hi> Theſe are the fineſt Tools out of <hi>Julian</hi>'s Shop, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined in <hi>Machiavels,</hi> with his [Divide and Rule:] As the <hi>Impoſing</hi> of <hi>Creeds</hi> uſher'd in the Pope at the firſt, to end Controverſies; ſo the <hi>Impoſing</hi> of <hi>Ceremonies</hi> may again uſher in Popery; As bloody <hi>Bonner</hi> ſaid, <hi>If they like our Pottage ſo well, we will make them eat our Beef alſo,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. The Differences betwixt the Brethren of the <hi>Presbyterial</hi> and <hi>Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gational</hi> Judgment, come next to be diſcours'd.</head>
               <div n="1" type="remark">
                  <p>
                     <hi>REmark</hi> the Firſt is, when the <hi>Reduction</hi> of <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> to its Primitive Form, by that <hi>Learned,</hi> Humble, Holy, Peaceble and Reverend Biſhop Doctor <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> was tendered, and conſented to by Dr. <hi>Holdſworth,</hi> Dr. <hi>Brownrigg,</hi> Dr. <hi>Reynolds,</hi> and other Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Doctors; It was greatly hoped, that this would have given Content: But the high-flown Prelate, neither ſo Gracious, nor ſo Learned, nor ſuch Lovers of the Church's Peace, as was that Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Primate</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> broke all the Meaſures for Accommodations, both at the latter end of K. <hi>Charles</hi> l's Reign, and at the beginning of K. <hi>Charles</hi> Il's Reſtoration: Hereupon the Brethren both of the <hi>Presbyterial</hi> and of the <hi>Congregational Way</hi> were conſtrained to ſhift, as well as they could, for themſelves.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="remark">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Remark</hi> the Second is, at or towards the end of K. <hi>Charles</hi> I's Reign, before the Civil Wars broke forth, the Brethren of both thoſe Perſwaſions, made their Joynt and Humble Applications to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> that then ſat at <hi>Westminſter,</hi> for Protection and Peace; which though <hi>Nonconformity</hi> had been for former Ages a <hi>Napthali,</hi> wreſtling continually for it, but could never obtain it at the <hi>Prelate</hi>'s Hand, yet now obtaineth it by God's Graciouſneſs at
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:51818:14"/> the Hands of this <hi>Healing Parliament,</hi> who indeed did not look upon thoſe two Perſwaſions, as two <hi>distinct Parties,</hi> (This is a meer Miſrepreſentation of them by capricious <hi>Conformity</hi>) they being really and in Truth but <hi>one</hi> and the ſame <hi>Party,</hi> having only made uſe of differing Expreſſions, to declare their own Minds each to other, and that without Schiſm, or ſetting up of <hi>Churches</hi> againſt <hi>Churches,</hi> but holding Communion one with another in their Members, as they had occaſion ſo to do, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="remark">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Remark</hi> the Third Dr. <hi>Stilling fleet</hi> doth indeed make the Breach wider betwixt thoſe Brethren, than it really was, ſaying, [in his Sermon of the <hi>Miſchief of Separation</hi>] that the <hi>Aſſembly of Divines</hi> urged their <hi>Diſſenting Brethren to comply with their Rules of Government, and charged them with Schiſm if they refuſed to do it.</hi> All which is a meer Miſ-report out of the Papers of Accommodati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, betwixt the Brethren of thoſe two Perſwaſions: For in Truth it was not the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> of <hi>Divines</hi> themſelves, but only (as one wittily calls them) a <hi>Subter Sub-Committee,</hi> who declared ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that tended towards the <hi>Allegation,</hi> as the private Opinion of ſome of them (wherein they might be miſtaken) but did not deliver it as the final Determination of the whole <hi>Reverend Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly.</hi> And the Dr. hath miſ-teported the matter of Fact; for the Order of <hi>Parliament,</hi> Nov. 6. 1645. which impowered the Committee to Act, inſtructed them (<hi>to endeavour an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, of the different Opinions of the Aſſembly in point of Church-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; and in caſe that cannot be done, to ſind out ſome way that tender Conſciences, not ſubmitting in all things, might be born with,</hi> &amp;c.) and the then <hi>Diſſenting Brethren</hi> profeſſed a plenary Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to the Subſtance of God's Worſhip, though they differed in ſome <hi>Punctilio's</hi> or ſmall Circumſtances of Church Government only. Yea, and after all the Alterations and Debates, between theſe two Perſuaſions in that <hi>Sub-Committee,</hi> it was at laſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, that the Brethren Diſſenting in ſmall points of Diſcipline, ſhould be Indulged.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="remark">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Remark</hi> the Fourth. As it may not be denyed, That ſome ſingle Perſons of both Perſwaſions were ſometimes too rigid and ſtiff in their Private Sentiments, ſuch as Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> was in his <hi>Gangrena,</hi> &amp;c. on the one hand, and ſuch as Mr. <hi>Sterny</hi> was in his <hi>Deliverance</hi> from the <hi>Northern Presbytery,</hi> on the other hand: So it cannot but be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, There were many more of both Perſuaſions that were very learned, and more wiſely moderate, inſtancing only in two of great
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51818:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> Figure among <hi>Presbyters,</hi> namely Reverend Mr. <hi>Thomas Coleman,</hi> a Member of that <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> who hath this Paſſage, (<hi>The Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian way, and thoſe that walk therein, I imbrace and love: The congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gational way, and thoſe that practiſe it, I approve and honour, both are alike to me</hi>) See his <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> to whom he preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon <hi>Job.</hi> 11.20. <hi>July</hi> 30.45. and reverend Mr. <hi>Charles Herle,</hi> the <hi>Prolocutor</hi> to the <hi>Aſſembly of Divines,</hi> ſaith thus, (<hi>The Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between us and our Congregational Brethren is not ſo wide as ſome ſuppoſe;</hi> we do but, with <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Lot, take ſeveral ways, we are</hi> (as <hi>Abraham</hi> ſpeaks) <hi>Brethren ſtill,</hi> and (as they were) <hi>ready to reſcue each other on all Occaſions from the Common Enemy;</hi> our Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, 'tis ſuch as doth at moſt but ruffle a little the Fringe, not any way rend the Garment of Chriſt; 'tis ſo far from being <hi>Fundamental</hi> that it is ſcarce <hi>material,</hi> &amp;c.) See his Epiſtle before his Treatiſe of <hi>Independency.</hi> And on the other ſide, the Prudence and Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of D. <hi>Thomas Goodwin,</hi> Mr. <hi>Jeremy Burroug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> &amp;c. is too well known to be here inſerted.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="remark">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Remark</hi> the Fifth, more particularly, both thoſe Perſuaſions do agree, (1) in having only ſuch <hi>Officers</hi> as <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, namely, <hi>Pastors</hi> and <hi>Teachers, Elders</hi> and <hi>Deacons.</hi> (2) Such Spiritual Cenſures of <hi>Admiſſion, Admonition,</hi> &amp;c. for guarding God's Ordinances, and for guiding his Flock, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (3) In liberty of elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their own Church-Officers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (4) In a Power to keep their own Congregations from being leavened, and the Ordinances of <hi>Chriſt</hi> from being polluted by Officers within themſelves; and ſo in many more material Points, too long here to relate, as may amply appear in the <hi>Heads of Agreement</hi> aſſented to by both. The only <hi>main</hi> Difference, wherein they <hi>diſagree,</hi> is about the <hi>last Appeal,</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their <hi>Claſſes</hi> or <hi>Synods</hi> be <hi>Authoritative</hi> for Cenſures, or only <hi>Suaſory</hi> and <hi>Conſultative,</hi> and in Caſe Advice be not followed, a <hi>Non-communion</hi> only proceedeth, in Caſes too difficult for ſingle Congregations: This Difference, Reverend Mr. <hi>Herle,</hi> in his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face before quoted, moſt excellently qualifies and extenuates, as neither a <hi>material,</hi> nor ſo much as a <hi>formal</hi> Difference; 'Tis, (ſaith he) <hi>but the better or the worſe way</hi> for the Exerciſe of the ſame <hi>Form</hi> of <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> that is the Queſtion: The [<hi>that it be</hi>] and [<hi>what it be</hi>] and [<hi>which it be</hi>] is agreed on among us: 'Tis but the [<hi>whoſe it be</hi>] we differ in; and herein too, not ſo much [<hi>whoſe it be</hi>] neither, as [<hi>where it be</hi>] whether in every Congregation apart, or of the <hi>ſame Men, joyned with the like of other Congregations</hi>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:51818:15"/> in a Synod, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And Mr. <hi>Herle</hi> there concludes thus, <hi>Whatever</hi> our <hi>Differences</hi> be, let not the Devil hold the <hi>Perſpective-glaſs,</hi> either to <hi>magnifie</hi> or <hi>multiply them:</hi> Let us <hi>pray them leſs,</hi> but not <hi>argue them more,</hi> &amp;c. Unto which let me add from another Hand, That <hi>this Difference</hi> about the <hi>laſt Appeal</hi> may be compared to <hi>that</hi> betwixt <hi>two Citizens</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> who conteſted in Diſcourſe, Which of them two ſhould go firſt into the Gates of ſome Foreign Remote City, as <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice,</hi> when poſſibly neither of them might ever have any Occaſion or Opportunity to go thither, ſo far from Home, at all: Accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly the <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> may not for many Ages have any Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for this <hi>last Appeal;</hi> and therefore Diſputes about it ought not to diſturb Publick Peace.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. Some General <hi>Remarks</hi> upon the Heads of this Late Happy Agreement betwixt the Miniſters of both thoſe Perſwaſions, now <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nanimouſly <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited in the tranſcendent Bond of Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of Spirit.</head>
               <div n="1" type="remark">
                  <p>THE Firſt <hi>Remark is,</hi> Long hath this Unity been laboured af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, even for many Years, both in City and Country; and tho thoſe Unhappy Differences have been moſt happily compoſed in ſome <hi>Countries,</hi> in this Nation, and amicable <hi>Agreements</hi> have been ſolemnly conſented unto, and comfortable Communion hath been carried on by Miniſters of both Perſwaſions; as in thoſe two remote Counties of <hi>Cumberland</hi> and <hi>Weſtmerland,</hi> in the Year 1656. And likewiſe in <hi>Yorkſhire</hi> and <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> afterwards, the former giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Light to the latter: Wherein, to my own perſonal Knowledg, that old Rule was not obſerved, (<hi>If the Bank will not come to the Boat,</hi> the <hi>Boat will not come to the Bank, that they might never meet</hi>) for there were mutual Condeſcenſions on both the <hi>Bank's-Side</hi> and on the <hi>Boat's-Side,</hi> &amp;c. Nor may I omit what Light was given to both theſe aforeſaid by that <hi>Chriſtian Concord</hi> managed by Reverend Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> in <hi>Worceſterſhire,</hi> before either of them, in the Year 1653. Likewiſe muſt I mention that candid Spirit in <hi>Apollonius,</hi> the <hi>Presbyter</hi> at <hi>Meidulburg</hi> in <hi>Zealand,</hi> manifeſted in his Learned and Loving Letter, to the five Authors of the <hi>Apologetical Narration, Tho. Goodwin, Phil. Nye, Guil. Bridge, Jer. Burrows, Sydrach Simp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> in the Year 1644. And Mr. <hi>John Norton</hi>'s friendly Anſwer to <hi>Apollonius</hi> in the Year 1645. from <hi>New-England.</hi> Thus this <hi>Spirit</hi>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:51818:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> hath been ſtriving and ſtrugling a long Time for Unity among Brethren, in the Country, both Foreign and Domeſtick, and ſome time hath prevailed; but now (<hi>Deo Gratias</hi>) it hath prevailed in this <hi>great City,</hi> which, I truſt, doth bode better things than <hi>Lewis Maimburgh</hi>'s <hi>Method</hi> of re-uniting Proteſtants and Papiſts did, firſt writ in French, and made to ſpeak Engliſh in this Day, when we were upon the very brinks of <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Slavery.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="remark">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Remark</hi> the Second. Seeing in Matters of Religion ſo little is got by wrangling Diſputation, therefore, for the avoiding of that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience, there ought to be an <hi>Agreement</hi> of ſome <hi>Principles</hi> on both Sides, wherein they do <hi>convenire in tertio,</hi> meet unanimouſly, as in a <hi>Third:</hi> Sure I am, ſuch a <hi>Cordial and Chriſtian Concord</hi> in all thoſe moſt <hi>Material Heads</hi> of <hi>Agreement,</hi> is the gaining of a grand Point againſt the Common Adverſary, who depends upon their own Harmony and our Diſcord and Diſtractions.</p>
                  <p>I cannot find any Reaſon why I may not, without Vanity, prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſticate <hi>good Things to come</hi> from this Happy Unity, conſidering,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. How God commanded his Bleſſing in <hi>David</hi>'s Day, when the <hi>two Houſes</hi> of <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>David</hi> came up, after eight Years Unnatural Inteſtin Wars, to <hi>dwell together as Brethren in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity;</hi> 'tis ſuppoſed that at the End of that <hi>Diſcord David</hi> penned his 133 <hi>Pſalm;</hi> after which the Kingdom of <hi>Iſrael</hi> flouriſhed more than ever before.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. How the two Sticks (<hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which had been a Cleft-Stick ever after <hi>Rehoboam</hi>'s Reign) became <hi>one Stick</hi> again, and clave cloſe together <hi>in the Hand of the Lord;</hi> tho this was but a poor Stick in it ſelf ſtill, yet God was pleaſed to uſe ſo ſlender a thing to very great purpoſe, as was fulfilled, when the <hi>Jews</hi> and many of the <hi>ten Tribes</hi> returned from the <hi>Captivity</hi> into their own Country under <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> and <hi>Ezra,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.16, 17, to 28. After which Unity <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> (Turk and Pope) are deſtroyed, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 38, and 39, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. How that old Fewd betwixt <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> was laid aſide by the <hi>Kingdom of the Goſpel,</hi> the <hi>Partition-Wall</hi> thrown down by <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s coming: As there was no <hi>Noiſe of Axe or of Hammer,</hi> in the Building of <hi>Solomon's Temple,</hi> 1 Kings 6.7. So nor ought to be in the erecting the <hi>Goſpel-Church;</hi> and indeed there was no Noiſe of Diviſion at its firſt Plantation, for the <hi>Builders</hi> thereof <hi>were all of one accord,</hi> Act. 4.22. There was <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitas cordis, oris &amp; operis,</hi> Unity of <hi>Heart, Mouth</hi> and <hi>Practice,</hi> &amp;c. Oh how plentifully was the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:51818:16"/> Spirit of Gifts and Graces poured forth, and what abundance of Converts came in to the Church daily, and the Goſpel ran like a Sun-Beam into all Parts of the World, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Dr. <hi>Lightfoot</hi> notes well, That at this Time all dividing Names were laid aſide; in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon the <hi>Acts,</hi> p. 293. I wiſh, with all my Soul, all <hi>dividing Names</hi> might be done away in our Day; as thoſe diſtinguiſhing Titles of <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Independants,</hi> were Nick-Names from Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; let them lay buried in Everlaſting Oblivion: Then may we hope a <hi>freſh Vein of Election</hi> (the want of which being ſo much complained of) might break forth as <hi>Life from the Dead,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="remark">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Remark</hi> the Third. I do cordially concur with Reverend Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> (whoſe Parts and Piety deſerve due Veneration) in his <hi>deſire</hi> that <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Men likewiſe would lay aſide their Prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and come into this <hi>Chriſtian Concord,</hi> ſaying, <hi>The diſtance is not ſo great,</hi> but <hi>all theſe three</hi> (<hi>the Epiſcopal, Presbyterian</hi> and <hi>Independant</hi>) <hi>were they but heartily willing and forward for Peace, they might agree: I know they might do it, having ſpoken with ſome Moderate Men of all the three Parties,</hi> and do perceive by their Conceſſions, <hi>it were an eaſie Work,</hi> &amp;c. 'Tis the Shame (ſaith he) of all our Faces, that this is not done for publick good, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s <hi>Gildas Salvianus,</hi> or <hi>Reform'd Pastor,</hi> p. 187. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Again (he ſaith) The <hi>Firſt</hi> hath been too fierce upon the <hi>Second,</hi> and the <hi>Second</hi> too ſevere againſt the <hi>Third,</hi> whereas the Truth perhaps muſt be gathered from the ſeveral Parties, who each of them hold a part of it in peculiar. See his <hi>Chriſtian Concord,</hi> p. 95, 96. And again, when God reſtor'd Peace to his Church, All the three ſhall ſee their own Miſcarriages, and lament them before the Lord, yea loath themſelves for their Emulations, pag. 101. And again, excellently, <hi>While God is my Maſter, his Word my Rule, his Work my Buſineſs, and the Succeſs of it in ſaving of Souls my End, I cannot be ſilent to ſee Souls undone by the</hi> Diſcord of Miniſters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> See his <hi>Reform'd Paſtor,</hi> p. 199. To which I add, no doubt but there be godly Miniſters of that Perſuaſion, who are right <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and not tinged with <hi>Arminianiſm, Socinian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm,</hi> &amp;c. Not differing from us in Fundamentals, but in Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantials only; Now when the <hi>day of Chriſt</hi>'s Power comes, that <hi>will make all Parties willing,</hi> Pſal. 110.3. this would cauſe the Concord to be ſo much the ſtronger; for a three-fold Cord is not eaſily broken.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="remark">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:51818:17"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Remark</hi> the Fourth. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity without Verity</hi> is rather a <hi>Conſpiracy,</hi> as in the <hi>Builders</hi> of <hi>Babel, Gen.</hi> 11.1, 4. which ended in Confuſion; there is no laſting Concord but in Truth. <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate</hi> were two Wood-Sticks that were made one in the <hi>Devils Hand</hi> (<hi>not in Gods,</hi> as <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah</hi> above) to beat <hi>Chriſt</hi> to Pieces. The Union Papiſts boaſt of is rather Politick than Real, having vaſt Vari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> among them in their moſt Potent Orders, as <hi>Franciſcans, Dominicans,</hi> &amp;c. but the Unity which <hi>Chriſt</hi> came to eſtabliſh, doth not depend upon <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> but upon <hi>Charity</hi> in a Chriſtian, and Candid Forbearance of one another in <hi>Circumſtantials:</hi> Where there is an Agreement in the Eſſentials of Worſhip, Indiſterent things are diſpenſed with for <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> Acts 21.24. And this Holy Unity is called the <hi>Conſolation,</hi> Acts 15.31. The Lord bleſs us with more of this <hi>Bleſſed Conſolation.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
